<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Cody Hatfield</title>
  
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/"/>
  <updated>2020-02-27T16:54:11.422Z</updated>
  <id>https://codyhatfield.me/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Cody Hatfield</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Health Exporter 1.1.0 Released</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2020/02/health-exporter-1-1-0-released/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2020/02/health-exporter-1-1-0-released/</id>
    <published>2020-02-27T16:54:11.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-27T16:54:11.422Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Health Exporter 1.1.0 is now released on the App Store.</p><p>This release allows you to export multiple data types at once into a single CSV file.</p><hr><p>Health Exporter is a simple iOS application that allows you to export iOS health data to a CSV file. See more details <a href="/apps/health-exporter.html">here</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Health Exporter 1.1.0 is now released on the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release allows you to export multiple data types at once into a singl
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>We Should Learn From RSS</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2019/11/we-should-learn-from-rss/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2019/11/we-should-learn-from-rss/</id>
    <published>2019-11-17T20:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-17T20:57:05.479Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="https://medium.com/offline-camp/we-should-learn-from-rss-31d100c81d26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Medium</a></em></strong></p><p><img src="/2019/11/we-should-learn-from-rss/cover.jpeg" class=""></p><p>Let's talk about RSS. You may have heard of it or seen it appear across the web. Perhaps you have always wondered what it is, or perhaps you already know all about it. No matter which it is, I want to talk about why you should care about RSS and why we should learn from it.</p><p><div class="video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RVG7zZpvYJY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p><h2>What is RSS?</h2><p>RSS is a web feed format that is used to distribute content across the web.<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup> Two types of content that are commonly distributed over RSS include blog feeds and podcasts.</p><p>If you have ever listened to a podcast, that episode you listened to was most likely distributed using RSS. You may even be reading this post using RSS.</p><h2>RSS Gives Control</h2><p>When content is consumed from the web, there are two players that matter: <strong>content producers and consumers</strong>. RSS empowers both and gives producers control over how they produce and distribute their content, while also giving consumers control over how they consume content.</p><p>With RSS, content producers can <strong>own their content</strong> while still successfully reaching consumers. Unlike other media industries, there is no need to give up ownership in order to increase distribution. A content producer can host their content wherever and however they like. This could be on their own servers under their own domain. Or maybe they own the domain but use a hosting service to host their content. Perhaps they use a large content management system or a statically generated site. No matter what they choose, they can simply publish an RSS feed to distribute their content to the open web.</p><p>RSS allows consumers to consume content however they prefer, without having to give up the convenience of discovering content. In other words, it allows consumers to bring their own <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_agent" target="_blank" rel="noopener">user agent</a>. The &quot;user agent&quot; in this case is an RSS reader or podcast player. Any user agent can be used to access the content from any content creator. Do you not like the changes your podcast player made in the latest update? Switch to another one while still being able to listen to the same podcasts. Did the RSS reader you were using for years announce they were stopping future development? Move your feeds to a different reader and pickup right where you left off.</p><p>The consumer can use whatever user agent they prefer and the content producer can produce their content however they like, without either caring what the other is doing. Both players have <strong>total control over how they use the web</strong>, while still being able to discover and connect to one another.</p><h2>Not having control</h2><p>RSS is the example I use when describing how the web should work. Just as useful is having a counter-example for how the web <strong>should not work</strong>.</p><p>My counter-example is <em>Medium</em>. This is ironic (or maybe hypocritical?) since I am producing this post using Medium and there is a high chance you are consuming this post using Medium.<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn2" id="fnref2">[2]</a></sup> Nevertheless, I hope you can see why Medium takes away control from both of us.</p><p>For content producers, Medium is both a writing tool and publishing platform. Producers must use the Medium editor in order to publish their content. Sure, we can write drafts using any tool we like, but eventually every post must be published using their editor. This means producers do not have full control over how their content is created and shown. My current frustration is the lack of support for footnote linking in Medium.<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn3" id="fnref3">[3]</a></sup> If you have ever used the Medium editor, you may think it works just fine for you; until it doesn't. I also do not own my content that is published to Medium. What happens if Medium goes away? What happens if they break links to my post?</p><p>As consumers, Medium takes away control over how you consume and discover content. There is a lot of great content on Medium. But, how can you discover and consume this content? You most likely are using the Medium website or mobile app. Today, Medium has support for subscribing to a blog using an RSS feed. But, what happens when they remove this functionality?<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn4" id="fnref4">[4]</a></sup> What happens when they add a <a href="https://help.medium.com/hc/en-us/articles/360018834314-Stories-that-are-part-of-the-metered-paywall" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paywall</a>? How do you discover content that is not on Medium? What about the content producers that do not want to publish on Medium?</p><p>The more content producers that use Medium, the more it pushes out consumers who do not. The more consumers that use Medium, the more it pushes out content producers that do not. This is not an open web. This is a closed web.</p><h2>Learning from RSS</h2><p>RSS is not perfect or even close to being perfect. And neither is the open web. But, I hope you can see how we can learn from RSS to build and use the web we want. For me, RSS is the best example to describe to others how I believe the web should work. No matter what your role is in the web, think about what <em>you</em> want the web to be. And maybe think about using RSS as your example, too.</p><p>As a consumer, think about <strong>supporting independent content creators</strong>. Does the platform you use to consume their content support them? If not, why not? Think about the reasons and tradeoffs being made when you use that platform.</p><p>As a content creator, think about the <strong>ownership of your content</strong>. Do you really own the content you are producing? Does the platform you use empower and give you control over your content? If not, think about why you use that platform? What benefits does it provide?</p><p>As a developer, think about why RSS has been successful. Why have podcasts been so successful while blog feeds are struggling to keep up with other platforms like Medium? How can this pattern be improved and applied to other areas of the web?</p><h2>Using RSS</h2><p>If you are just learning about RSS and want to start supporting it more, I encourage you to checkout different RSS readers and podcast players. Some RSS readers I use are <a href="https://nnw.ranchero.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NetNewsWire</a> and <a href="https://reederapp.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reeder</a>. My main podcast player is <a href="https://overcast.fm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Overcast</a>. A quick web search will bring up many different options.</p><hr class="footnotes-sep"><section class="footnotes"><ol class="footnotes-list"><li id="fn1"  class="footnote-item"><p>Atom is another web feed format. Personally, I use the term RSS even when what I am talking about applies to both. Just note they are different formats that try to accomplish the same thing. <a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></p></li><li id="fn2"  class="footnote-item"><p>This post also exists on my <a href="https://codyhatfield.me">personal blog</a>. However, this Medium post is the canonical link. Medium has support for <a href="https://help.medium.com/hc/en-us/articles/360033930293-Set-a-canonical-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">canonical links</a> to make sure this pattern does not harm content discovery and search engines. To be fair, Medium has many tools today that play fair with the open web. But, what is the net effect? <a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></p></li><li id="fn3"  class="footnote-item"><p>Isn't it annoying to have to scroll back and forth between footnotes? Thanks for coming down here anyway! <a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></p></li><li id="fn4"  class="footnote-item"><p>Did you know <a href="https://mashable.com/2012/09/05/twitter-api-rss/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.wprssaggregator.com/facebook-to-remove-rss-feeds-as-from-june-23-2015/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Facebook</a> used to support RSS? Hmm. <a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></p></li></ol></section>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/offline-camp/we-should-learn-from-rss-31d100c81d26&quot; target=&quot;_bla
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>EV Road Trip: Charging</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2019/09/ev-road-trip-charging/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2019/09/ev-road-trip-charging/</id>
    <published>2019-09-24T02:35:21.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-24T03:02:48.598Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is part of a series of posts about a recent road trip I took in my Tesla Model 3. You can see a list of all posts in the series <a href="/categories/EV-Road-Trip/">here</a>.</em></p><hr><h2>Planning</h2><p>The assumption most people make when learning someone has gone on a long road trip in an EV is that there must have been a lot of planning involved. They imagine spending a few hours laying out the exact route ahead of time. Every stop to charge must be pinned on a map and printed out, right? And if you deviate from the route, you will most definitely run out of charge and be stranded? Once you are on the route, it must be stressful? Whatever you do, do not take a wrong turn!</p><p>Planning is definitely required. The amount of planning is more than an internal combustion engine (ICE) car. However, once you have gone on a few trips it is really not that stressful, nor does it take much extra planning time. There are two main steps I take on a trip that is more than 300 miles:</p><ol><li>Beforehand, check to make sure a route actually exists</li><li>Before leaving a charging station, know where your next stop is</li></ol><p>The first step is pretty straightforward. I like to use <a href="https://abetterrouteplanner.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A Better Routeplanner</a> to check routes beforehand. Tesla also has their own <a href="https://www.tesla.com/trips" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trip planner</a> as well as the in-car navigation. With a Long Range Model 3 (310 miles on a single charge) and the Tesla Supercharging Network, it is rare to find a route in the US or Europe that is not possible to drive without stopping for an impractical amount of time. There are still a few routes that are impractical, however. Mainly in the Dakotas, Northern Montana, and Central Canada. Tesla has spent years deploying the <a href="https://www.tesla.com/supercharger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Supercharging Network</a> with over 1,500 stations. They will continue to expand it for years to come, both to increase capacity and eliminate those impractical routes.</p><p>Once I know the trip is possible and practical, I am done planning until the trip starts. I do not bother planning each and every stop. Where I stop really depends on how hungry I am, what time of day it is, or how tired I am. These are the same as any road trip. The only planning I do during the trip is deciding what my next stop will be before departing from a charging station. This is mainly to make sure I always leave a charging station with enough charge to reach the next. The in-car navigation makes it pretty difficult for this to happen. It knows where you are trying to go, how much charge you currently have, and can predict fairly accurately how much energy you will use while driving. It will warn you if you try to leave without enough charge, and will even tell you how much longer to wait before it is safe to leave for the next stop. As the charging network grows, this will become less of an issue. Soon, you will be able to decide where to stop as you are driving, similar to waiting until the gas light comes on before thinking about where to find the nearest gas station.</p><h2>How long did you have to stop and charge?</h2><p>Ask yourself, when driving for 45 hours across four days, how many times will you stop and for how long?</p><p>On my road trips I normally stop to either go to the bathroom or eat a meal. Bathroom breaks are pretty quick: around five minutes. Stopping to eat varies, but is usually around 30 minutes. I prefer to make <em>some</em> stop every 1.5 to 2 hours. Most of those would be bathroom breaks and every five hours would be a meal. The cycle of stops would look something like this:</p><ul><li>First 5 minute bathroom break</li><li>Second 5 minute bathroom break</li><li>30 minute food break</li><li>Repeat</li></ul><p>What would a 45-hour drive look like?</p><ul><li>18 bathroom breaks (90 minutes)<figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">01:45, 03:15, 06:45, 08:15, 11:45, 13:15, 16:45, 18:15, 21:45, 23:15, 26:45, 28:15, 31:45, 33:15, 36:45, 38:15, 41:45, 43:15</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>8 food breaks (4 hours)<figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">05:00, 10:00, 15:00, 20:00, 25:00, 30:00, 35:00, 40:00</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure>So for a 45-hour drive, that is approximately <strong>26 stops for a total length of 5.5 hours.</strong></li></ul><p>But, what happens if I am driving an electric car? Charging is slow, so I need to stop for much longer, right?</p><p>Most people I talk to assume that charging an electric car is just like filling a car with gas, only it takes much longer. This is the intuitive way to think: compare a new, unknown experience with a familiar experience that seems similar. On a long road trip in an ICE car, for example, you would drive along until your tank is low, quickly stop to fill it up, and continue on your way. It is so fast to fill up that the total amount of time you spend getting gas is negligible.</p><p>When and how you charge an electric car on a road trip is different. A large reason is because charging is much slower mile-for-mile than filling a gas tank. We just looked above at how long we would stop on a 45-hour road trip. This stopping does not include the time to get gas because, again, that is negligible. However, the time spent charging an EV is not negligible, so we should keep track and add the time spent charging as well, right? Let’s look at this at a fundamental level. When not driving, either:</p><ul><li>Our car would be parked doing nothing while we eat a meal; OR</li><li>Our car would be charging while we do nothing</li></ul><p>Here’s an idea: instead of stopping to only charge or only eat, let’s stop to <strong>charge and eat at the same time</strong>. Sounds simple, right? If it is so simple, I encourage you to think about why the number one question I have been asked after going on my trip is: “how long did you have to stop and charge?” Nobody asks, “how long did you stop and eat for?” For the most part, they share the same answer.</p><p>This is the fundamental idea that <a href="https://www.tesla.com/supercharger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tesla Superchargers</a> are based on.</p><blockquote><p>Stop along the world’s fastest charging network while you grab a quick bite to eat.</p></blockquote><p>They are located between urban areas and nearby restaurants for you to stop and eat. The charging speed is extremely fast compared to typical charging situations at home (up to 80x faster than a 120v outlet). So, how do they affect road trips? Well let’s take a look at the 45-hour drive I just did.</p><ul><li><strong>Total number of stops:</strong> 20</li><li><strong>Time spent charging:</strong> 6.5 hours</li></ul><p>As you can see, using superchargers makes road trips for EVs fairly close to ICE cars. Interestingly, the number of stops I took was much less than what I projected it to be in an ICE car. Some of this can probably be attributed to the fact I stopped and charged overnight. The total time spent charging was about 18 percent longer than the estimated time to stop with an ICE car. And this is <a href="https://www.tesla.com/blog/introducing-v3-supercharging" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only getting better</a>.</p><h2>Waiting to charge</h2><p>I acknowledge there are a lot of assumptions when estimating the stopping time for an ICE car. This number could vary quite a bit from what I calculated. A better way to look at this is to compare the amount of time required to charge against the amount of time needed to stop. The difference between these is the <strong>time spent waiting to charge.</strong><figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">(Time spent charging) - (Time needed to stop) = Time waiting to charge</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p><p>This is the time that really matters.</p><p>I was originally going to try and measure this time during my trip, but I found it difficult and distracting from the trip itself. The best I could come up with for “time needed to stop” is the estimate above: 5.5 hours.</p><p><figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">6.5 - 5.5 = 1.0 hours waiting to charge</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p><p>While I do not have any hard data to back this up, it feels about right from my experience.</p><p>The big remaining question is: <strong>what will it take for this number to reach zero?</strong> There are two major improvements I see that, if implemented, will make this number zero or <em>less</em>.</p><ol><li>Increase the charging speed of short breaks</li><li>Dedicated chargers for each car</li></ol><h3>Increase the charging speed of short breaks</h3><p>From my data, bathroom breaks had:</p><ul><li>An average charging speed of <strong>372 miles per hour</strong></li><li>An average charging time of <strong>14 minutes</strong></li></ul><p>Tesla <a href="https://www.tesla.com/blog/introducing-v3-supercharging" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has announced</a> the next iteration of superchargers will allow a Long Range Model 3 to charge 75 miles in five minutes. That is an average of <strong>900 miles per hour</strong> over five minutes. If all the superchargers I used at bathroom breaks had this rate of charge, the average charging time would have been approximately <strong>6 minutes</strong>. In total, this would have saved <strong>1 hour and 10 minutes</strong> over the entire trip.</p><p>If you remember from above, the estimated time spent waiting to charge was <strong>1 hour</strong>. We are now below zero.</p><p><figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">(6.5 - 1.16 saved from faster bathroom breaks) - 5.5 = -10 minutes waiting to charge</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p><h3>Dedicated chargers for each car</h3><p>Of course, the rate above only happens in the <em>ideal</em> scenario. There are a few factors that can affect charging speed. The first factor I experienced quite often last winter was having a cold battery. If the battery is too cold, it cannot accept as high of a charging input. However, this has recently been addressed with a feature called “On-Route Battery Warmup” that was announced alongside V3 Supercharging. Teslas will now use excess heat from the motor to warm the battery slightly before arriving at a Supercharger station. Tesla claims this decreases the average charging time by <a href="https://www.tesla.com/blog/introducing-v3-supercharging" target="_blank" rel="noopener">25 percent</a>. This was the second trip since I received this feature, and I can certainly tell the difference. Just by downloading a free, over-the-air update, my car now charges 25 percent faster at all Supercharger stations. There was no trip to the service center and no purchase required.</p><p>The largest remaining factor that affects charging speed is sharing a charger with a nearby car. Many people do not realize this, but there is actually only one charger for every two charging stalls at a Supercharger station. Each <em>charger</em> currently has a maximum power output of 150 kW, not each <em>stall</em>. This means if a car is charging in each stall they will share that power.</p><p>I experienced this a couple of times on my trip and it was definitely noticeable. For some part of the charge I had to share power with another vehicle at both Rock Springs, WY and Ritzville, WA. The average charging speed at Ritzville got as low as <strong>191 miles per hour</strong>. If I had a dedicated charger, I could have saved <strong>16 minutes</strong> of charging time at a single stop.</p><p>The great news is V3 Supercharging is solving this problem as well. Every stall will have a <strong>dedicated charger</strong> capable of up to 250 kW. No sharing with a neighboring car and no worrying about which spot to park in. That means short, bathroom breaks will have a consistent, fast charge no matter how busy the station.</p><hr><p>Supercharging already makes road trips in an EV very comparable to ICE cars. With a little more planning and slightly longer stops, EV road trips are just as convenient. The continuing expansion of new locations along with V3 Supercharging are the last steps needed to make EV road trips as simple as the trips we have all taken in ICE cars.</p><p>Of course, they are just a <a href="/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/">little more fun</a>, too.</p><p>Interested in seeing the raw data from my road trip? Check it out <a href="/data/ev-road-trip/">here</a>.</p><p>Questions or suggestions? Feel free to DM me on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/codynhat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">@codynhat</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is part of a series of posts about a recent road trip I took in my Tesla Model 3. You can see a list of all posts in the se
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="EV Road Trip" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/categories/EV-Road-Trip/"/>
    
    
      <category term="tesla" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/tags/tesla/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>EV Road Trip: For the Fun of It</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/</id>
    <published>2019-08-21T07:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-24T02:44:57.585Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Update:</strong> <em>This post is part of a series of posts about a recent road trip I took in my Tesla Model 3. You can see a list of all posts in the series <a href="/categories/ev-road-trip/">here</a>.</em></p><hr><p><img src="/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/images/teton-tesla-model-3-dashcam.png" class="" title="Grand Tetons from Model 3 Dashcam"></p><p>I recently drove a 2700 mile road trip alone with my electric vehicle: a Tesla Model 3. Many people have asked me why I would want to drive from Seattle, Washington to Steamboat Springs, Colorado. Even my own family members chose flying over riding with me. Someone even asked if the gas was more expensive than a plane ticket 😏.</p><p>There is quite a bit of information and opinions out there about electric vehicles. I have had my Model 3 for almost a year and many people have asked me questions about my experience. People are always very curious, yet the questions they ask tell me that most people do not know enough about electric vehicles. Even with all the information out there people are having their fears blown way out of proportion, are being misled, and even have outright false information.</p><p>This is why I chose to drive 2700 miles instead of buying a plane ticket. We are all overwhelmed with information these days. Information coming from the first-hand experience of someone you know will be more memorable than misleading articles you see online. I hope to share my experience with the people I know, so they may start asking different questions. Our planet and future generations depend on it.</p><hr><h2>Benefits? What benefits?</h2><p>There is, of course, another reason I deciding to pass on the plane ticket. <strong>Electric vehicles are just fun to drive.</strong> There is no other way to put it. I would choose driving my car over any other form of transportation in almost any scenario.</p><p>The questions people ask are always about common concerns with electric vehicles. They never ask about the benefits. What I have come to realize is most people do not know what the benefits are, yet even realize they exist. The pros-and-cons list in people’s heads looks something like this:</p><p><img src="/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/images/pros-cons.png" class="" title="Perceived EV Pros and Cons"></p><p>This is completely normal. Electric vehicles are new and different. <strong>We are scared of what is different and tend to focus on it.</strong> People were skeptical of the original iPhone because it <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2008/05/regarding_the_iphone_keyboard" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t have a keyboard</a>. Whoa, different. Scary. Does anyone remember using a phone with a physical keyboard?</p><p>Electric vehicles are currently seen as a compromise. They are better for the environment, but I have to give up <em>a lot</em> to have one, right? Well, let’s spend some time looking at that other list that people tend to forget.</p><p>More specifically, I would like to share some benefits I experienced throughout my road trip, many of which I experienced for the first time.</p><h2>Cost of fuel</h2><p>I will start by getting this out of the way. Most people I talk with understand this benefit pretty well. In fact, most see it as basically the only benefit. Nevertheless, it is always great to see some real-world data. <strong>How much cheaper is an EV road trip compared to the same road trip in a internal combustion engine (ICE) car?</strong></p><p>We will start by estimating the cost of driving 2700 miles in a comparable ICE car. Let’s start with the following assumptions:</p><ul><li>28 MPG for a car comparable to a Model 3</li><li>Average of $2.85 per gallon</li></ul><p>With those values, driving 2700 miles would cost about <strong>$275</strong> with a cost per mile of <strong>$0.10</strong>.<figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">2700 miles / 28 miles per gallon = 96.4 gallons of gas</span><br><span class="line">96.4 gallons * $2.85 = $275</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p><p>Looking at the <a href="/data/ev-road-trip/">data from my road trip</a>, the total charging cost came to <strong>$98</strong> with a cost per mile of <strong>$0.04</strong>.</p><p>This comparison is not perfect, but gives us a good idea about the difference in cost. Keep in mind that cost will vary depending on how you drive and the price of fuel. The cost of electricity at Tesla Superchargers varies by location at a state-wide level and has <a href="https://electrek.co/2018/03/11/tesla-increases-cost-supercharger/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">occasional</a> <a href="https://electrek.co/2019/01/18/tesla-increases-supercharger-prices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">price</a> <a href="https://electrek.co/2019/01/22/tesla-cuts-supercharger-prices-back-down-customer-backlash/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">adjustments</a>.</p><p>Tesla has a useful calculator on their <a href="https://www.tesla.com/supercharger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">website</a> for comparing the cost of supercharging. There are also great tools for estimating the cost of an EV trip; my favorite being <a href="https://abetterrouteplanner.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A Better Routeplanner</a>.</p><h2>Ain’t No Mountain High Enough</h2><p>Driving through mountain passes in an electric car is one of the best driving experiences I have ever had. Much of this is due to <a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2018/09/30/regenerative-braking-is-one-of-the-joys-of-driving-an-ev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">regenerative braking</a>.</p><p>Every manufacturer of hybrid and fully-electric vehicles implements regenerative braking differently, so it is hard to generalize the experience across all EVs. The basic idea is that an electric motor in your vehicle can also act as a generator. When you want to slow down, this generator will start to convert the kinetic energy of your moving vehicle into electrical energy to charge the battery, slowing down the vehicle in the process. The “when you want to slow down” is very different across vehicles. Some require the driver to use the brake pedal, a certain gear setting, or a stalk on the steering wheel.</p><p>In a Tesla, the only vehicle with regenerative braking that I have experience driving, all regenerative braking is controlled by the accelerator pedal. When you let off the accelerator, regenerative braking will be applied instead of letting the car coast. This allows you to precisely control the speed of the car by only using the accelerator pedal. The only time I use the brake pedal is when I come to a complete stop at intersections and when I need to slow down in a hurry.</p><p>So, how is this related to driving through mountain passes? Well, whenever you drive down a mountain or large hill in a ICE car, how do you drive differently? Maybe you downshift to lighten the load on your brakes? Perhaps you just keep your foot on the brake pedal, switching between coasting and braking throughout the descent?</p><p>For my car, the experience driving down a hill is the same as any other. No shifting, coasting, or <strong>even using the brake pedal</strong>. All I have to do is use the accelerator pedal to control precisely what speed I want to go. And thanks to regenerative braking, I do not even need to use the brake pedal when going down a steep mountain pass. I just let off the accelerator a little more than normal and that is it. Not only is an EV not using any energy when driving downhill, but it is actually <em>gaining</em> energy by recharging the battery. This often happens over long distances and without ever using the brake pedal.</p><p>There was a point in my trip where I averaged -10 watt hours per mile of energy consumption over five miles of driving.</p><p><img src="/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/images/ev-downhill-regenerative-braking.jpg" class="" title="[EV Regenerative Braking]"></p><p>The projected range was a comical 999 miles. Seems like Tesla needs to replace that with an ∞ symbol.</p><p>Having precise control of downhill speed makes the driving experience down mountain passes a lot of fun. It was easy and safe to pass trucks and other slow vehicles, and fun to not have to slow down 20 miles per hour around corners thanks to the precise speed control and tremendous handling from the weight of the battery pack.</p><p>Of course, going <em>up</em> mountain passes was fun, too. Again, it was easy to precisely control speed going up steep mountain passes. This time due mostly to tremendous horsepower, torque, and acceleration from the two electric motors. No shifting, awkward automatic transmission, or increase in engine noise. It really does not even feel like you are going uphill. You may even wonder why everyone else on the road has started to slow down so much.</p><h2>“Please Turn Off Engine”</h2><p><img src="/2019/08/ev-road-trip-for-the-fun-of-it/images/no-idling.jpg" class="" title="[Source https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.roadtrafficsigns.com]"></p><p>I love coming across signs like this. I have experienced this before a number of times when waiting for a draw bridge or taking a ferry. I also experienced this again on my trip.</p><p>Idling sucks. It is a waist of fuel and pollutes harmful toxins in our air, often near places with heavy traffic and many pedestrians. You can turn off your engine when sitting in traffic to avoid idling. Or maybe your car will automatically do it for you. Neither of these are perfect solutions. Ask yourself: when sitting in traffic why don’t you turn your engine off? Maybe it is too inconvenient? Are you worried about not being able to turn it on back in time? What if your engine fails to start again? Having your car automatically turn the engine off isn’t the best solution either. If it was so great, why doesn’t everybody use it?</p><p>One more thing you don’t need to worry about if you drive an electric car. There is no engine to start and nothing to “turn on”. It is just a simple switch from <em>park</em> to <em>drive</em>. If you are still worried about switching from park, just let the car “hold” the brake for you. It is just a simple tap on the accelerator to continue moving forward.</p><p>On my way home from Colorado, I decided to drive through Yellowstone National Park. Unfortunately, there was a major car accident in the park as I was making my way through. Traffic came to a dead stop while the main road was closed down to one lane for a couple of hours.</p><p>We would end up sitting in one spot for ten to fifteen minutes before moving up a little at a time. The waits were long enough that everyone decided to turn their engines off, but short enough that drivers had to pay attention and be ready to turn on their engines at any time. There were always those one or two cars that were not ready in time and backed up traffic for a few car lengths. It didn’t really matter in the end, but it is the small things that count! Since I could switch to drive at a moment’s notice, I usually waited until two or three cars ahead started moving before switching.</p><p>It was the evening and still a little warm out. Most cars would leave windows unrolled and engines off, including myself. As the evening went on, the bugs started to come out. Eventually, I rolled up my windows and turned on the air conditioning. No problem. For the ICE cars, they had to compromise. They could continue to keep windows unrolled and deal with the mosquitoes. They could also roll the windows up and turn on the air conditioning and engine. Or they could roll up the windows, leave their engine off, turn on the fans and risk running their battery down.</p><p>This may not matter to everybody, but the little things add up. And when you are already in a stressful situation, like stuck in traffic in the middle of nowhere, one less decision to make goes a long way.</p><hr><p>This first post has gone over a few of the benefits of taking an EV on a road trip. I hope you have learned something new and are one step closer to being comfortable owning an EV.</p><p>There are a few other posts I have planned in this series that will cover some of the concerns surrounding electric vehicles, Tesla-specific features, and deep dives into nerdy, technical details. So stay tuned!</p><p>Questions or suggestions? Feel free to DM me on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/codynhat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">@codynhat</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;This post is part of a series of posts about a recent road trip I took in my Tesla Model 3. You can see a li
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="EV Road Trip" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/categories/EV-Road-Trip/"/>
    
    
      <category term="tesla" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/tags/tesla/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>AirSecure — Own Your One-Time Passwords</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2019/02/airsecure-%E2%80%94-own-your-one-time-passwords/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2019/02/airsecure-—-own-your-one-time-passwords/</id>
    <published>2019-02-27T08:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-04-04T02:48:03.420Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post originally appeared on Textile's <a href="https://medium.com/textileio/airsecure-own-your-one-time-passwords-a65efd612dc6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Medium</a></em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on Textile&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/textileio/airsecure-own-your-one-time-passwords-a65efd612dc6&quot; 
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="external" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/tags/external/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>WWDC 2018: A Guide to Siri Shortcuts</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2018/07/wwdc-2018-a-guide-to-siri-shortcuts/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2018/07/wwdc-2018-a-guide-to-siri-shortcuts/</id>
    <published>2018-07-31T07:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-04-04T02:48:27.221Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post originally appeared on Hiya's <a href="https://medium.com/hiya-inc-engineering-blog/wwdc-2018-a-guide-to-siri-shortcuts-9b6ee8f00f4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Medium</a></em></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on Hiya&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/hiya-inc-engineering-blog/wwdc-2018-a-guide-to-siri-shortcuts-9b6
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="external" scheme="https://codyhatfield.me/tags/external/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Why I Think Snapchat&#39;s Model is Flawed</title>
    <link href="https://codyhatfield.me/2014/10/why-i-think-snapchat-s-model-is-flawed/"/>
    <id>https://codyhatfield.me/2014/10/why-i-think-snapchat-s-model-is-flawed/</id>
    <published>2014-10-16T21:25:01.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-03T14:46:18.533Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="https://medium.com/@codynhat/why-i-think-snapchats-model-is-flawed-c50998ffd590" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Medium</a></em></strong></p><p>A few days ago, a large amount of Snapchat photos and videos were leaked online in what is being called “The Snappening.” Snapchat immediately sent out a statement saying they were not responsible for the leak and the blame should be set on third-party apps.</p><p>A third-party application named <em>Snapsaved</em> took responsibility, admitting their servers were breached and 500MB worth of images was accessed.</p><p>Ever since Snapchat has become popular, there have been a number of third-party applications built that use Snapchat’s API. Some of these apps allow Snapchat users to send and receive snaps on devices and platforms they normally couldn’t. Some of these apps, such as Snapsaved, allow users to download and save snaps without the sender knowing. This defeats the whole purpose of Snapchat, photos disappearing a few seconds after being viewed. This is also a big threat to the privacy of Snapchat’s users, which is why they are trying to get rid of any third-party apps that use their API.</p><p>An API, or Application Programming Interface, is what a mobile app uses to connect to the “cloud,” or a company’s servers. It can be thought of as a web browser for computers. Instead of a human typing in a url like <em>http://facebook.com</em> and getting back a nice looking web page, an API uses a url like <em>http://api.facebook.com</em> and gets back a bunch of data. It then transforms or uses this data in a way that is useful to a user. The url an API uses is no different than the url a human uses when browsing the web. Because of this, a human could type in an API url if they wanted. All you would see is text that probably doesn’t make much sense.</p><p>Third-party apps do just this. They browse the internet using urls that are meant for computers and not humans.</p><p>This capability is perfectly fine in most cases, and in a lot of cases is even supported by companies. Sites such as Facebook and Twitter allow and encourage third-party apps to connect to their API. However, Snapchat does not.</p><p>The reason for this is obvious. Snapchat’s entire user experience centers around the idea that when you send a photo, it is only shown for a few seconds and then disappears forever. These photos are encrypted and stored on Snapchat’s servers. When someone views a snap, it is downloaded to their phone, shown for a few seconds, and then deleted from their phone and from Snapchat’s servers. Sounds simple, right? Problems arise when third-party apps start browsing Snapchat’s API. These apps can download photos with a user’s username and password, just like the Snapchat app. But once the photo is downloaded, Snapchat cannot guarantee that it gets deleted forever. In the case of Snapsaved, they save user’s photos on their servers.</p><p><em>Third-party apps that allow users to save the snaps they receive are the reason why thousands of photos have been leaked</em>.</p><p>This is the approach that Snapchat has taken when trying to explain the situation to the press and to their users. They are telling users to not trust any third-party apps that ask for your username and password. They have even started contacting Apple and Google to try and ban any third-party apps from being on their app stores.</p><p>But not all third-party apps are to blame.</p><p>A few months ago, I started working on a third-party Snapchat application for Mac OS X called Snappy. We realized that there was no way to view or send snaps from your computer. There was no Snapchat website or desktop app, only the mobile app.</p><p>We saw an opportunity.</p><p>Snappy was released to the Mac App Store in June of 2014. It allowed people to view snaps from their friends and send snaps using the built-in camera on their computers. You could also apply stylish and funny filters to your photos before sending them. Snappy did not allow you to save snaps and did not prevent snaps from disappearing. It worked exactly like Snapchat. The photos disappeared after they were shown.</p><p><img src="/2014/10/why-i-think-snapchat-s-model-is-flawed/snappy.png" class="" title="Snappy, Snap from your Mac"></p><p>We had no intention of interfering with Snapchat’s model or putting people’s privacy at risk; two things that other third-party apps do.</p><p>Instead, we wanted to enhance the experience of Snapchat by simply allowing people to use it on their computers. And we did this quite successfully.</p><p>Snappy peaked in the U.S. charts as the number three social networking app available to download. We exceeded our initial goal of downloads, set before even starting development. And we did this without spending a penny on marketing or advertising. (Actually, we wasted $10 on Facebook advertisements that only turned into a handful of downloads)</p><p>We have spent countless number of hours on Snappy. What started as a fun side project for a few college students turned into a project much larger and much more time demanding than we first anticipated.</p><p>With the recent events and press surrounding Snapchat’s leak, we decided to remove Snappy from the App Store.</p><p>Even though we had no involvement in the leak, we had one of the most popular Snapchat third-party apps and one of the only ones available for the Mac.</p><p>From the beginning, we only wanted to enhance the core experience of Snapchat. We decided that leaving Snappy on the App Store would only go against Snapchat’s wishes. We did not want to be in the middle of anything or contribute to ruining the experience of Snapchat. After all, this only started as a small side project.</p><p>So, I say to everyone aware of the recent Snapchat leak, do not put the blame on all third-party apps like Snapchat says.</p><p>Do not put the blame on Snapchat or their lack of security, but instead put the blame on their model. They thought they could make photos posted to the internet “disappear.” This seemed like a reality until third-party apps started going against Snapchat’s wishes and invading the privacy of their users.</p><p>To the third-party apps allowing people to save snaps, I say great job invading the privacy of millions of people. And thank you for making the countless hours we have put into Snappy come crashing down.</p><p>I hope it was worth it.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@codynhat/why-i-think-snapchats-model-is-flawed-c50998ffd590&quot; ta
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
